George and Ira Gershwin Collection
Music Division, Library of Congress
Guides to Special Collections in the Music Division of the Library of Congress
George and Ira Gershwin Collection 1895-2008 (bulk 1920-1960)
ML31.G38
Gershwin, George, 1898-1937
Gershwin, Ira, 1896-1983
60,000 items 136 containers 53 linear feet
Music Division Library of Congress Washington, D.C.
Composer George Gershwin (1898-1937) and his lyricist brother Ira (1896-1983) wrote some of the most significant American popular songs of the first half of the twentieth century. Working with novelist and poet DuBose Heyward, they created the great American opera Porgy and Bess. Additionally, George Gershwin composed several singularly American concert works, including An American in Paris and Rhapsody In Blue, and both brothers produced many distinguished songs working with other collaborators. The George and Ira Gershwin Collection contains music manuscripts, handwritten and typewritten lyric sheets, printed music, correspondence, photographs, programs and publicity materials, legal and financial documents, and thirty-one scrapbooks, which present nearly a complete record of the Gershwins' lives and work as they were chronicled in the contemporary press.
Selected Search Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the Library's online catalog. They are grouped by name of person or organization, by subject or location, and by occupation and listed alphabetically therein.
People
Armitage, Merle, 1893-1975--Correspondence.; Bennett, Robert Russell, 1894-1981.; Botkin, Benjamin Albert, 1901-1975--Correspondence.; Botkin, Henry Albert, 1896-1983--Correspondence.; Corbett, Rosamond Walling Tirana, 1910-1999--Correspondence.; Daly, William, d. 1974.; Damrosch, Walter, 1862-1950--Correspondence.; DePackh, Maurice, 1896-1960.; Gershwin, George, 1898-1937--Archives.; Gershwin, George, 1898-1937--Correspondence.; Gershwin, George, 1898-1937--Photographs.; Gershwin, George, 1898-1937.; Gershwin, George, 1898-1937.; Gershwin, George, 1898-1937. Porgy and Bess.; Gershwin, George, 1898-1937. Porgy and Bess.; Gershwin, George, 1898-1937. Selections.; Gershwin, George, 1898-1937. Selections; arr.; Gershwin, Ira, 1896-1983--Archives.; Gershwin, Ira, 1896-1983--Correspondence.; Gershwin, Ira, 1896-1983--Photographs.; Gershwin, Ira, 1896-1983.; Gershwin, Ira, 1896-1983.; Gershwin, Ira, 1896-1983. George and Ira Gershwin collection. 1895-2008.; Gershwin, Rose--Correspondence.; Heyward, DuBose, 1885-1940.; Kaufman, George S. (George Simon), 1889-1961.; Pringle, Aileen, 1895-1989--Correspondence.; Ryskind, Morrie, 1895-1985.; Saddler, Frank.; Sirmay, Albert--Correspondence.; Sirmay, Albert.; Spialek, Hans.; Swift, Kay, 1897-1993.; Tamber, Selma--Correspondence.; Weill, Kurt, 1900-1950--Correspondence.
Subjects
Composers--United States--Autographs.; Composers--United States--Correspondence.; Composers--United States.; Lyricists--United States--Correspondence.; Lyricists--United States.; Musical films.; Musicals--Scores.; Musicals--Vocal scores with piano.; Musicals.; Revues.
Form/Genre
Artifacts (Object genre); Correspondence.; Financial records.; Legal documents.; Photographic prints.; Programs (Documents); Scrapbooks.
Administrative Information
Provenance
The George and Ira Gershwin Collection has been assembled over a period of more than seventy years from a number of sources, foremost among them, members of the Gershwin family. The first acquisition that would become part of the Gershwin Collection was George's 2-page holograph sketch for Roll Dem Bones (or, "The Crap Shooter's Song") from Porgy and Bess, donated by Ira in 1939. The next gift, and the first substantial one, was received in 1953 from the estate of Rose Gershwin, consisting of George's holograph scores for six of his seven large-scale orchestral works: An American in Paris, Concerto in F, Cuban Overture, Porgy and Bess, Rhapsody in Blue, and Second Rhapsody. Ira's first major gifts were George’s custom-made desk and Ferde Grofé's holograph score for his symphonic orchestration of Rhapsody in Blue, also in 1953, and George's holograph score for the "I Got Rhythm" Variations, in 1954.
During the 1950s, '60s, and '70s, Ira donated numerous music manuscripts, lyric sheets, photographs, sound recordings, and other materials in his possession, many of them accompanied by his informative explanatory notes. He also donated the drafts for his memoir, Lyrics on Several Occasions, in 1966, and he purchased and donated several items that he considered interesting and appropriate for the collection.
By the early 1980s, as Ira's advancing age was diminishing his activity on behalf of the Gershwin Collection, his wife, Leonore, became increasingly involved with collecting and preserving the Gershwins' documentary legacy. In 1983, she purchased George's holograph two-piano score for An American in Paris, which she donated the following year.
After Ira's death in 1983, Leonore continued and expanded her husband’s efforts, donating the remaining music manuscripts and lyric sheets (some 6,000 documents) from their home in 1987. She purchased and donated George's letters to Julia Van Norman in 1988. Her final gift, in the spring of 1991, included an early tune book of George’s sketches for An American in Paris. Following her death later that year, the Library of Congress received from her estate self-portrait oil paintings of both brothers, posters from the 1950s international tour of Porgy and Bess, one of George's pianos, and thirty-one scrapbooks that document the careers of George and Ira and productions and performances of their work from 1913 until 1986.
Many other members of the Gershwin family and friends of the Gershwin brothers have also given materials for the collection. The following list is by no means comprehensive. Albert Sirmay donated the working annotated typescript libretto for Porgy and Bess in 1955 and his letters from Ira in 1963. Kay Swift donated the holograph manuscript of the George Gershwin Songbook, as well as a large quantity of George's holograph music sketches in 1966. Arthur Gershwin's gifts in 1966 and 1968 included forty-seven photographs belonging to George and a memorial scrapbook assembled by Rose Gershwin. Mabel Schirmer donated her letters from George in 1974. Leonore Gershwin, Frances Gershwin Godowsky, Judy Gershwin, and Marc George Gershwin jointly donated the so-called Secaucus Manuscripts (a large cache of music manuscripts and lyric sheets found in a Warner Brothers warehouse in Secaucus, New Jersey) in 1984. Leonore Gershwin and Frances Gershwin Godowsky donated the Congressional Gold Medals honoring George and Ira in 1985. Michael Feinstein’s donations included George's holograph manuscript score for a dance sequence from Rosalie in 1990 and two original Duoart piano rolls. Rosamond Walling Tirana donated her correspondence with George Gershwin in 1993. Dorothy Botkin Rosenthal and Daniel Botkin donated an important collection of correspondence, photographs, and other materials in 1998. Leopold Godowsky III donated scores from George's library in 1987, and he and Elaine Godowsky donated a manuscript for the Concerto in F in 2004. Michael and Jean Strunsky presented George's "little black book" in 2009.
Since 1991, Ira and Leonore's acquisitions work has continued, underwritten by the Ira and Leonore Gershwin Trust for the Benefit of the Library of Congress. In some instances, the Trust has acquired and donated materials; in numerous other instances, the Library has purchased materials using funds provided by the Gershwin Trust.
The most remarkable gift from the Gershwin Trust was a collection of more than 120 previously unknown documents from the estate of Emanuel Alexandre, for many years Rose Gershwin’s attorney, presented to the Library of Congress in 1997. The Gershwin Trust also donated two pages of sketches for songs from Girl Crazy in 1998, and five letters at various times.
Materials purchased by the Library with funds from the Gershwin Trust include the archival files of the Theatre Guild (1927-1966) concerning Porgy and Bess, purchased in 1992, notable manuscript sketches for Porgy and Bess from the estate of Kay Swift, purchased in 1994, and seven additional music manuscripts, as well as rare printed scores, contracts, and sixty-one letters, postcards, and other documents.
Finally, the Library's acquisitions funds were used in 1990 to purchase a collection of approximately 275 contracts, letters, and other documents ( 1919-1949 ) from the files of the law offices of Wattenberg and Wattenberg, attorneys for music publisher Max Dreyfus and the publishing firm Chappell and Co. (for many years the Gershwins' principal publisher). In 1996, the Library purchased three music manuscripts and four letters with funds provided by the Library’s James Madison Council.
Other Repositories
Additional correspondence, business papers, photographs, programs, and other documents are held by the Ira and Leonore Gershwin Trusts in San Francisco, CA. Materials concerning Porgy and Bess are included in the DuBose Heyward Papers at the South Carolina Historical Society. Research and publication materials for The Gershwin Years are included in the Edward Jablonski and Lawrence D. Stewart Collection at the Harry Ransom Humanities Research Center at the University of Texas at Austin.
Related Material
The Ira Gershwin Files from the Law Office of Leonard Saxe
relate primarily to Ira's personal legal affairs and the activities of the Rose Gershwin Testamentary Trust from 1948 to 1968. The Ferde Grofé Collection contains materials for Rhapsody in Blue, including Grofé's holograph score for his original jazz band scoring. Additional materials are also found in
the Serge Koussevitzky Archive
,
the Moldenhauer Archives at the Library of Congress
, the Spivacke Fund Collection,
the Vernon Duke Collection
, and The Danny Kaye-Sylvia Fine Collection.
Access and Restrictions
The George and Ira Gershwin Collection is open to research. Researchers are advised to contact the Music Division prior to visiting in order to determine whether the desired materials will be available at that time.
Certain restrictions to use or copying of materials may apply.
Biographical Note
Date Event
1872? Moishe Gershovitz (later, Morris Gershovitz, then Gershvin, and finally, Gershwin) is born in St. Petersburg, Russia. He immigrates to New York in the early 1890s. George will describe him as "a very easy-going, humorous philosopher who takes things as they come."
1875 or 1876 Rosa (later, Rose) Bruskin (or Brushkin) is born in St. Petersburg, Russia. She immigrates to New York with parents Gershon and Mariaska (later, Mary) Dechinik Bruskin and younger siblings Bernard "Barney" and Katiel "Kate" in the early 1890s. George will describe her as "nervous, ambitious, and purposeful" and "never the doting type."
1895 July 21 Morris Gershovitz and Rosa Bruskin are married in New York.
1896 December 6 Ira Gershwin is born Israel Gershovitz in Manhattan's Lower East Side. He is known as "Izzy" or "Iz," mistakenly believing (until applying for a passport in 1928) that his given name is Isidore (or Isadore). Ira follows his father's use of the surname Gershvin until 1917, when he adopts Gershwin.
1898 January 15 Morris and Rosa Gershvin become naturalized U.S. citizens.
1898 September 26 George Gershwin is born Jacob Gershwine in Brooklyn, New York. (Gershwine is probably an alternate spelling of Gershvin and not a change of the family name; in the 1890s in the New York's Russian-Jewish immigrant communities both spellings would be pronounced "Gershvin.") By 1913, George is using the name Gershwin, which the entire family eventually adopts. His family sometimes calls him Georgie, although there is scant evidence that he is ever called Jacob.
1900 March 14 Arthur, the third Gershwin sibling, is born.
1900 October 3 Leonore "Lee" Strunsky is born into a Russian-Jewish family in San Francisco. Lee and her parents, Albert and Mascha Strunsky, and her older sister, Emily, move to New York in 1906, following the famous earthquake. Lee’s brother, English, is born in New York in 1908. Emily will later become one of George’s dearest friends.
1906 December 6 Frances (known as "Frankie"), the youngest Gershwin child and only daughter, is born.
Early 1900s Ira's emerging personality is quiet and studious. He becomes an avid reader and also develops an interest in theater (moving pictures as well as stage shows). George is more rambunctious and misbehaves frequently. He describes his first awareness of music as hearing Rubinstein's Melody in F at a penny arcade in Harlem (ca. 1904), and he credits a performance of Dvořák's Humoresque (ca. 1908) by schoolmate-violinist Maxie Rosenzweig (later, Max Rosen) as having "opened the world of music" to him.
Circa 1910 The family acquires a piano, with the expectation that Ira will continue piano lessons begun a short time before under the tutelage of Rose's sister, Kate Wolpin. George surprises his family by demonstrating keyboard ability, acquired by experimenting on the player piano at the home of a friend. George begins piano lessons, while the plans for Ira's continued study are discarded. The details of George's early piano instruction remain uncertain and accounts disagree. George's first lessons may have been with an unnamed neighborhood teacher for a short time, then with a Mrs. Louis Greene, and followed by a period under a Hungarian band leader and operetta conductor named Von Zerly.
1910-1914 Ira attends Townsend Harris Hall high school. In 1913, he and Isadore Hochberg (later, lyricist E. Y. "Yip" Harburg) write the "Much Ado" column for the school's literary magazine, the Academic Herald. In October 1913, Ira is listed as one of the publication's four art editors.
1912 George enters the High School of Commerce.
1912-1913 George begins attending concerts by the likes of Leopold Godowsky, Josef Lhévinne, Leo Ornstein, and Efrem Zimbalist during his freshman year in high school.
Circa 1913-1918 George's first important piano teacher is Charles Hambitzer, who George will describe as "the first great musical influence in my life." Lessons probably begin in early 1913 and continue until Hambitzer's death in 1918, although how frequently, particularly in the later years, is not certain.
Circa 1913 George composes his earliest known songs, to lyrics by Leonard Praskins: Ragging the Traumerei and Since I Found You (now lost). Sources disagree as to which song was first, although Ragging the Traumerei is widely accepted as George's earliest surviving composition.
1914-1916 Ira attends the City College of New York, majoring in English. In November 1915 he and Yip Harburg begin writing a column for The Campus, the City College weekly journal titled, "Gargoyle Gargles," signed by "Yip and Gersh."
1914 March 21 George makes his first documented appearance as a pianist on a concert program presented by the Finley Club, the literary society of the City College of New York, performing an original tango and accompanying a singer.
1914 May Fifteen-year-old George, already skilled at sight-reading and transposing, leaves the High School of Commerce to become a piano pounder at Jerome H. Remick and Company, at a salary of $15 per week.
1914 September 26 Ira's first publication in a commercial newspaper, the New York Mail, is credited to "Gersh."
Late 1915 George begins making piano rolls for the Standard Music Roll Co. From 1915 until 1925 or 1926, he makes some 140 piano rolls, more than half of them in 1916 and 1917. Initially, he records the works of other composers, but after 1919 he concentrates chiefly on his own music, and exclusively so after 1921.
1915 or 1917, through 1921 or 1923 George studies music theory with Edward Kilenyi, Sr. Again, sources disagree as to the precise dates.
1916-1918 Ira works at his father’s Turkish baths and at B. Altman’s department store, taking occasional evening classes at City College. He attends numerous Vaudeville shows and moving pictures, and he publishes some light verse.
1916 Piano rag Rialto Ripples, written by George and collaborator Will Donaldson, is George's first complete surviving instrumental piece, and his earliest repertoire work.
1916 May George's first published song, When You Want 'Em, You Can't Get Em, When You've Got 'Em, You Don’t Want 'Em (lyric by Murray Roth), earns a total royalty of $5.00.
1916 June George's second published song (and his first to be sung in a Broadway show) is Making of a Girl (lyric by Harold Atteridge) in The Passing Show of 1916 at the Winter Garden.
1917 March 17 George quits his job as a song plugger at Remick's, wishing to associate himself more closely to what he describes as "production music, the kind Jerome Kern was writing."
1917 May 23 Ira's first known song lyric, You May Throw All the Rice You Desire, is published in the New York Evening Sun; Ira is credited as I. B. Gershwin.
1917 July George becomes rehearsal pianist for Miss 1917. During the next eighteen months or more, he accompanies rehearsals for a number of shows, acquainting himself with the theater and many of its important figures.
Late 1917 George is pit pianist for several weeks at the Cocoanut Grove Roof of the Century Theatre, for an all-Spanish review with music of Quinito Valverde.
1917 November Ira begins a several-month stint as an occasional Vaudeville reviewer for the New York Clipper.
1917 December Ira writes his first lyrics to melodies of George's. His diary names one such lyric, You Are Not the Girl (now lost). Later in the month, the diary mentions "a couple" of songs written with George, but the titles are not given.
1918 February George joins the music publishing firm T. B. Harms Co. as a staff composer. George, Ira, and Lou Paley collaborate on A Beautiful Bird, the earliest surviving George-and-Ira song. Only the melody and lyric are preserved, however.
1918 February The Shrine, a brief "filler" piece and Ira's first publication for which he is paid, appears in The Smart Set: A Magazine of Cleverness. Ira is credited as Bruskin Gershwin; he earns $1.00.
1918 September Some Wonderful Sort of Someone (lyric by Schuyler Greene) becomes the first of George's songs published by T. B. Harms. The following month it is heard in Ladies First at the Broadhurst Theatre, along with The Real American Folk Song (Is a Rag), the first George-and-Ira song performed in a Broadway show, and the earliest George-and-Ira song to survive as a complete piano-vocal score.
1918 December 9 The first musical to feature George's songs, Half Past Eight (three songs with lyrics by Edward B. Perkins, and one by Ira), closes out of town at the Empire Theatre in Syracuse, New York, after only one week and a scathing review in Variety.
1919 George continues writing songs that he hopes may be interpolated into Broadway musicals. I Was So Young (You Were So Beautiful) (lyric by Irving Caesar and Al Bryan) was one of two songs by George included in Good Morning, Judge at the Shubert Theatre. It is the first of George's songs to achieve some popularity.
1919 May 26 La-La-Lucille! (lyrics by Arthur J. Jackson and B. G. DeSylva) opens at the Henry Miller Theatre in New York. George's first book musical and his first full-scale Broadway production, the show is a moderate success, running for 104 performances.
1919 Fall? George and lyricist Irving Caesar write Swanee in an effort to capitalize on the current one-step rage, Hindustan. The song is included in the Capitol Revue at New York’s new 5,300-seat Capitol Theatre, but it attracts little notice. In December, Al Jolson hears it at a party and decides to interpolate it in his current hit show, Sinbad. The song then becomes an immediate success and George's first international hit.
1920 August 31 Waiting for the Sun to Come Out, the first published George-and-Ira song, is introduced in The Sweetheart Shop at New York’s Knickerbocker Theatre. The sheet music credits Ira as "Arthur Francis," a name that Ira would use for the next 3-1/2 years. Ira devised the pseudonym (combining the names of his younger brother and sister) in an effort to avoid the accusation of attempting to trade on his better-known brother’s reputation.
1921 May 3 Two Little Girls in Blue (music by Vincent Youmans and Paul Lannin) opens at the George M. Cohan Theatre. It is Ira’s first successful Broadway show, running for 135 performances.
1921 Summer In his continuing desire to increase his musical training, George takes summer courses at Columbia University: Nineteenth-Century Romanticism in Music, and Elementary Orchestration, taught by music department head Rossetter G. Cole.
1922 August 28 Blue Monday, a one-act opera with lyrics by B. G. DeSylva, receives its first performance as part of George White's Scandals of 1922 at New York’s Globe Theatre. Sometimes described as George's first serious work and the precursor to Porgy and Bess, it is deemed out of keeping with the rest of the revue, and it is cut after only one performance.
1923 January George studies musical form and composition with arch-traditionalist Rubin Goldmark. Most sources indicate that the course of study lasted for only three lessons.
1923 April 3 The Rainbow (lyrics by Clifford Grey) opens at London’s Empire Theatre. George makes his first trip to Europe to supervise the production.
1923 November 1 George makes his concert hall debut accompanying mezzo-soprano Eva Gauthier in a "Recital of Ancient and Modern Music for the Voice." George accompanies her in a set of American songs, including some of his own and, it is said, steals the show. The concert (or a version of it) was later repeated in Boston, London, and Derby, Connecticut.
1924 February 12 Rhapsody in Blue receives its first performance at New York's Aeolian Hall by Paul Whiteman's Palais Royal Orchestra, with Whiteman conducting and George as piano soloist. The not-yet-begun work is announced as a "jazz concerto" in the January 4 New York Tribune. George completes his score in less than three weeks; it is then orchestrated by Ferde Grofé. Tentatively titled American Rhapsody, it is retitled Rhapsody in Blue at Ira's suggestion. It is an immediate popular triumph, although critics are somewhat less enthusiastic. The performance is repeated on March 7 and at Carnegie Hall on April 21. George records the work for the Victor label (his first phonograph recording) with Whiteman and his orchestra.
1924 May Ira drops the pseudonym Arthur Francis. He chooses the name Ira, wanting to keep his initial I, and feeling that Isidore and Irving were too common. Imagine Me Without My You (music by Lewis Gensler), sung in Top Hole at New York's Fulton Theatre, becomes the first published song with lyrics attributed to "Ira" Gershwin (in this instance, Ira B. Gershwin).
1924 September 3 Be Yourself (music by Lewis Gensler and Milton Schwarzwald) opens at the Sam H. Harris Theatre in New York. It becomes the first complete Broadway musical with lyrics by "Ira Gershwin," enjoying a moderately successful run of 93 performances.
1924 September 11 Primrose (lyrics by Ira and Desmond Carter) opens at London's Winter Garden. It runs for 255 performances and becomes the Gershwins' first big London success, as well as their first show to be printed as a complete piano-vocal score.
1924 December 1 Lady, Be Good!, starring the brother-and-sister team of Fred and Adele Astaire, opens at New York's Liberty Theatre. It is the first complete George-and-Ira show on Broadway and its successful run of 330 performances is by far the Gershwins' longest to date.